对我们来说画出
It's going to be useful for us to draw pictures of what's
在运行时发生在程序中
happening in a program at runtime
为了理解微妙的问题。
in order to understand subtle questions.
其中一个问题就是
And one of those questions is the difference
在改变值和重新分配变量之间。
between mutating a value, and reassigning a variable.
我们将使用一个称为快照图的符号。
We're going to use a notation called a snapshot diagram.
以最简单的形式，一个快照图
And in simplest form, a snapshot diagram
显示程序中的每个变量——如n和list--
shows each variable in the program-- like n and list--
一个箭头从变量指向它的值。
with an arrow pointing from that variable to its value.
这个值可能是一个基元类型，所以n是一个int，
That value might be a primitive type, so n is an int,
所以这些整数只是简单的数字。
so these integers are just written as simple numbers.
或者它可能是一个对象类型，所以
Or it might be an object type, so
list指向数组列表。
list points to an array list.
我们把它画成一个圆圈
And we show that as a circle that
其中包含类型的名称。
has the name of the type in it.
但对象值通常有自己的内部变量，
but object values often have their own internal variables,
我们会用箭头指出
and we'll use arrows pointing out
以显示这些内部变量的值。
in order to show the values of those internal variables.
例如，一个整数数组
So for example, an array list of integers
对数组中的每个元素都有一个引用
has essentially a reference for every element of that array
列表。
list.
在这个特殊的时刻，
And at this particular point in time,
列表中有三个元素
there are three elements in that list-- so we'll
索引它们0、1和2。
index them 0, 1, and 2.
它们指向其他值，3，10，和5。
And they point to other values, 3, 10, and 5.
现在，这门课的图表都是
Now, the diagrams in this course are all
从Java代码的示例中，
going to come out of examples from Java code,
但这个符号实际上是通用的。
but this notation is actually really general.
这是一种思考变量和值的通用方法，
It's a general way of thinking about variables, and values,
以及编程中的对象，因此
and objects in programming, so you
可以用于多种不同的语言。
can use it for a variety of different languages.
现在，它将给我们一种可视化的方法
Now, it's going to give us a way to visualize
改变变量之间的区别，
the difference between changing a variable,
重新分配变量，并更改
reassigning a variable, and changing
一个值——它改变了一个对象的内部结构。
a value-- that is changing the internals of an object.
所以当你给变量赋值时
So when you assign to a variable, what you're doing
正在更改变量箭头指向的位置，
is changing where the variable's arrow points,
你可以把它指向一个不同的值。
and you can point it to a different value.
最初，当我们声明并初始化为3时，
So initially, when we declare and initialize it to 3,
这是箭头，因为箭头指向3。
this is arrow, n as arrow points to 3.
但当我们重新分配时
But then when we reassign it, when
我们计算冰雹序列的下一个值，
we compute the next value of the hailstone sequence,
例如，将n重新指定为10，
for example, and reassign n to 10,
这意味着箭会消失，现在
that means this arrow goes away, and now there's
指向10的箭头。
an arrow pointing to 10.
当我们做下一步的时候，就是除以2
And then when we do the next step, which is to divide by 2
再加上5，我们去掉指向10的箭头，
and get 5, again, we get rid of that arrow pointing to 10,
我们把新箭头指向5。
and we point the new arrow to 5.
所以我们不会改变这些数字--
So we're not changing these numbers--
我们要做的是改变n的箭头指向。
what we're doing is changing where n's arrow points.
这就是作业的作用。
That's what an assignment does.
现在，当我们改变可变值的内容时
Now, when we change the contents of a mutable value
对于一个有内部变量的对象，我们所做的
of an object that has internal variables, what we're doing
正在更改从该值内部指向的箭头。
is changing the arrows that point from inside that value.
这叫做值的变异。
And that's called mutating the value.
例如，对于一个列表，我们首先创建这个列表，
So for example, for a list, we create that list initially,
里面什么都没有。
and it has nothing in it.
当我们给它添加一个元素时，
And when we do an add of an element to it,
好吧，这将从元素0创建这个箭头
well, that's going to create this arrow here from element 0
值为3。
to the value 3.
如果我们加上5，这里就会有一个箭头
And then if we add a 5, that's going to create an arrow here
从元素1到值5。
from element 1 to value 5.
如果我们再回去，那就是
And then if we go back and set, that is
将索引0处的元素更改为9，
change the element at index 0, and point it to 9 instead,
好吧，这样就可以摆脱这只箭了，
well that will get rid of this arrow,
它将指向9。
and it will point to 9, instead.
在所有这些列表中，list变量是
You notice in all of this that list, the list variable is
仍然指向同一数组列表
still pointing to the same array list
反对。所以我们不会重新分配这个变量，
object. so we're not reassigning this variable,
就像我们重新分配n一样。
the same way that we were reassigning n.
现在有些是可变的--对不起，
Now some of these are variable-- sorry,
我们使用的一些对象是不可变的，
some of these objects that we work with are immutable,
其中一些是可变的。
and some of them are mutable.
那就是说，我们能不能改变它们的内部结构？
So that means, can we change their internals or not?
所以对于字符串，我们可以重新分配一个变量
So for strings, we can reassign a variable
指向一个字符串对象，但我们不能
that points to a string object, but we can't actually
更改该字符串对象的内部。
change the internals of that string object.
所以当你运行这样的代码时
So when you run code like this, that
在字符串末尾添加一个字母，它实际上是什么
adds a letter to the end of a string, what it's actually
创建一个新的字符串对象，
doing is creating a fresh string object,
表示扩展字符串，
representing that extended string,
并将变量s重新分配给新的string对象。
and reassigning the variable, s, to that new string object.
字符串是不可变类型的示例--
String is an example of an immutable type--
它的值永远不允许更改。
it's a type whose values are never allowed to change.
这个对象的内部永远不能
The internals of this object can never
一旦他们被创造出来就改变。
change once they've been created.
不变性是一个主要的设计原则
Immutability is a major design principle
在这门课上我们要谈很多。
we're going to talk about a lot in this course.
在快照图表中，我们将
In a snapshot diagram, we're going
在对象上使用双边框
to use a double border on the object
表明它是不可变的--
to indicate that it's immutable--
你不能打开它改变里面的东西。
that you can't crack it open and change what's inside.
相比之下，还有另一个班
By contrast, there's another class
在Java中称为字符串生成器。
in Java called String Builder.
字符串生成器也表示
And String Builder also represents
一系列字符，但它有
a sequence of characters, but it has
允许您更改该对象的值的方法，
methods that allow you to change the value of that object,
就像我们改变的一样
the same way that we were changing
上面这个数组列表的值，
the value of this array list up here,
可以更改字符串生成器的值。
you can change the value of the String Builder.
所以你可以从一个字符串生成器开始，
So you can start with a string builder that's just a,
现在当你在上面加上一个b，
and now when you append a b to it,
你没有得到一个新的字符串生成器对象--
you're not getting a fresh String Builder object--
就像我们在弦上做的——你实际上
like we did for strings-- you're actually
更改字符串生成器。
changing that String Builder.
所以现在s b实际上是这里的a b，
So s b now actually means a b here,
因为它指向一个值已更改的对象。
because it's pointing to an object whose value is changed.
所以这两个快照图看起来非常不同。
So these two snapshot diagrams look very different.
很好，因为这些代码
And that's good, because these bits of code
实际上表现得很不一样。
actually behave very differently.
易变性与不变性的区别
The difference between mutability and immutability
将在我们的代码制定过程中发挥重要作用
is going to play an important role in making our code
不会有虫子。
safe from bugs.
所以现在，除了不可变的值之外，可变的类型
So now, in addition to immutable values, mutable types
和string一样，Java也给了我们
like string, Java also gives us the ability
创建不可变引用。
to create immutable references.
这些变量只能分配一次，然后
And these are variables that can only be assigned once, and then
以后再也不调。
never reassigned afterwards.
我们使用关键字final来表示我们想要
We use the keyword final to indicate that we want
一个不可变的变量。
a variable to be immutable.
Java编译器必须自己证明
The Java compiler has to prove to itself
你的最终变量只分配一次。
that your final variables is only going to be assigned once.
如果不能证明的话
And if it can't prove that, it's going
产生静态错误。
to produce a static error.
所以final实际上给了你静态检查
So final actually gives you static checking
对于不可变引用。
for immutable references.
在快照图表中，我们将
In a snapshot diagram, we're going
再次使用双线表示不能更改
to use, again, a double line to indicate that you can't change
一旦我们
this-- we're not going be able to move this arrow once we've
开始，指向5。
started, and pointing to 5.
现在，注意我们可以有一个不可变的引用
Now, notice we can have an immutable reference
一个可变的值。
to a mutable value.
例如，如果我们改变了字符串的声明
So for example, if we changed this declaration of String
在这里建造者，所以它有最终的结果，
Builder here, so that it had final in it,
这个箭头会变成双箭头，
this arrow would turn into a double arrow,
也就是说某人总是会指出这个价值，
and it would say that sb will always point to this value,
将始终指向此对象。
will always point to this object.
但是字符串生成器对象的内部
But the internals of the String Builder object
仍然可以改变。
can still change.
所以某人总是会指那里，但是
So sb will always point there, but it
可能意味着不同的字符序列。
may mean a different sequence of characters.
相反，我们可以有一个可变的引用
Conversely, we can have a mutable reference
一个不变的值。
to an immutable value.
这就是这里发生的事情--
And that's exactly what was going on here--
s是可变引用。
s is a mutable reference.
这不是最后的决定。
It's not final.
但它只指向这些不可变的值，
But it only ever points to these immutable values,
这些不变的字符串，永远不会改变。
these immutable strings, which will never change.
无论何时申报，使用final都是很好的做法
It's good practice to use final, whenever we declare
一个参数的方法，对于尽可能多的局部变量
the methods of a parameter, and for as many local variables
因为我们可以逃脱。
as we can get away with.
比如变量的类型，比如int
Like the type of the variable, like the int
在这里，这个最终声明实际上是
here, this declaration of final is actually
重要文件。
important documentation.
这对代码的读者很有用
It's useful to the reader of the code, which
使代码更容易理解，
makes the code easier to understand,
它由编译器进行静态检查
and it's statically checked by the compiler-- which
让它更安全。
makes it safer from bugs.
所以冰雹序列中有两个变量--
So we've got two variables in this hailstone sequence--
我们有n个名单。
we've got n and we've got list.
问题是，我们可以宣布哪些是最终的？
Question is, which of these can we declare final?
我们将在下一个练习中讨论这个问题。
We'll look at that in the next exercise.